

Brig Gagan Deep Singh Baath

Chandigarh
Mobile No: +91-8393886150
E-mail: sunnybaath05@gmail.com

Leading Change for Growth - Oriented, Organizational Structures

STRATEGIC LEADER, ENGAGED IN HUMAN RESOURCE & ORGANIZATIONAL DEVELOPMENT

STRATEGIC MANAGEMENT | LEADERSHIP | TRANSFORMATION | RECRUITMENT | CHANGE MANAGEMENT

EXECUTIVE SUMMARY

Accomplished leader, with 30 Years of experience in people & resource management. Maximizing the potential of the employees to drive growth, a highly ethical, value driven leader who improves business returns by innovating human capital with the intellectual horse power needed to negotiate ambiguity and paradox. Develop and attract, enrich and retain the best talent needed to capacitate business for sustainable growth and profitability. Deep understanding of critical business drivers; big picture visionary with ability to deliver with discipline and effectiveness.

Core Competencies

- Strategic Planning
- Organizational Development & Effectiveness
- HR Policy, Process & System Design
- Talent Management & Leadership Development
- Work Force Planning & Development
- Rightsizing & Restructuring
- Performance Management
- Compensation & Benefits

Education & Certificates

Civil

- Current Research Fellow

 Organizational Behavior &
 Human Resource Management),
 Indian Institute of Management,
 Kozhikode 2020
- Masters in Management Studies (Osmania University) - 2013
- M. Sc (Defence Studies), Madras University - 2000
- B. Sc (JNU), National Defence Academy, Khadakwasla - 1990

Military Courses

- Higher Defence Management Course, College of Defence Management (CDM), Secunderabad-2013
- Senior Command Course, College of Combat, Mhow - 2006
- Defence Services Staff College, Wellington – 2000

CAREER PROFILE & KEY HIGHLIGHTS

Strategic Leadership

- 'Single Star Flag Rank', commanded and provided the 'Operational Vision & Direction', to a 'Independent Infantry Brigade Group' (6-8K Troops) of the Indian Army, deployed as Theatre reserves in Northern Command (J&K), while performing in an ambiguous and challenging operational environment.
- Commanded an Infantry Battalion (800 Troops) in High Altitude on the Indo-China Border at Nathu-La (Sikkim), during active border skirmishes and face-offs. Steered multiple Indo-China Border Personnel Meetings (BPMs), established robust civil-military relations at the State level to accomplish strategic infrastructural development projects in the border areas and assisted operationalization of the Indo-China Border Trade at the Nathu-La (Bilateral Trade Aggrement-2006).

Institution Building & Transformation

- Raised, Re-structured, Re-configured and Re-oriented the first Independent Square Infantry Brigade Group of Indian Army (4-5 x Infantry Battalions, Artillery Regiment, Field Engineer Company, Supply & Transport Company, Surveillance & Target Acquisition Battery, Field Ambulance, Communications & Signal Company and other logistic support elements), to include the manpower planning, equipment profiling, training & development for optimum employment during a two-front threat scenario in Ladakh.
- Nurtured excellence, through **institutional strengthening, capacity building, transformation** & **modernization** of the Brigade Sized Force during active operations.

Strategic Estimates & Operations Management

- As the Colonel General Staff (Col GS) of an Infantry Division (15-18K troops), operating as part of the Strike Corps along the Western Front, oversaw the formulation of strategic estimates to include military intelligence, planning of military operations, conduct of innovative & realistic training in an environment of budgetary constraints, equipment management, formulation and meticulous execution of various Operational Directives & Standard Operating Procedures.
- Framing & reviewing the Army's Budget and provision of necessary fiscal inputs for finalization of LTPP (Long Term Perspective Plan) and Five Yr Plans.
- 'Operations Management' to include planning and implementation of a robust Internal Security, Disaster Management and Aid to Civil Authorities at the Apex level, while posted as the General Staff Officer (Operations) at the Military Operations Directorate at Army Head Quarters, New Delhi. Planning and execution of Out of Area Contingency Operations (OOAC), for humanitarian & military assistance, while combating security related and disaster relief situations.

Officers Cadre Management and Recruitment Operations

- Automated and Managed the performance appraisals, promotions, postings and statutory complaints of 2500 + Officers at the 34 Category A - Training Institutes of the Indian Army to include Indian Military Academy & Army War College, while undertaking the assignment of the Deputy Military Secretary at the Army Training Command, Shimla.
- As the Deputy Director General Recruitment (Estates), South Zone responsible for conduct of recruitment operations in the States of Tamil Nadu, Andhra Pradesh, Telangana & UTs (Pondicherry & Andaman Nicobar Islands), reviewed the current recruitment operations & best practices of the Indian Army, established the Jt Working Mechanisms with the State Govts and designed an effective public perception campaign to recruit high calibre skilled manpower for the allocated 10K plus vacancies in the South Zone.

Leadership Development

- As a 'Single Star Staff Officer' posted at Army Training Command, conceptualized and planned the Indian Army's Junior Leadership Training, Professional Military Education of officers and designed tailor-made Leadership Development Programs for the Mid-Ranked and Senior Army officers, duly incorporating innovative training methodologies and contemporary best practices.
- As the Directing Staff (Colonel) **Designed and Developed the leadership and 'Staff Functions' programs for the emerging leaders** at the Defence Services Staff College, (DSSC), Wellington.
- Coached, mentored and imparted cutting edge training to the Officers at the Infantry School, Mhow, a Premier Indian Army Training Institution and a Centre of Excellence.

International Experience

- Appointed as the Chief Operations Officer (MONUC), United Nations Mission in Democratic Republic of Congo and functioned in a multicultural & diverse international environment.
- The officer has been closely associated with **Multi-National Planning Augmentation Training/Exercises (MPAT)** and other International Peacekeeping Training Endeavors at the Centre of UN Peace Keeping (CUNPK), New Delhi, India. The officer has extensive experience in **joint training with foreign armies to incl the IDF (Israel Defence Force) and British Army.**

Research - Organizational Behavior & Human Resource Management

• Current Research Fellow in a PHD Program at the prestigious Indian Institute of Management, Kozhikode (NIRF-2021, Rank 4th Institute), with particular focus on Leadership & Organizational Development, Organizational Structures & Culture, HR practices, Change Management and Ambidextrous Organizations.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

♦ <u>Directing Staff, Higher Command Wing, Army War College (Apr 2022- Till date)</u>

• Trained and Mentored, select 100 x Colonels of Indian Army in Higher Defence, Strategic Management and Operational Art at the Army War College, Mhow.

♦ Deputy Military Secretary, Army Training Command, Shimla (May 2020 - Mar 2022)

- Automated and Managed the performance assessments, promotions, postings and statutory complaints of 2500 + Officers at the 34 x Category A Training Institutes of the Indian Army to include Indian Military Academy & Army War College.
- Maintenance of Service Records & Validation of the Qualitative Requirements for officers posted at Various Category A Training Establishments of the Indian Army.
- Processed the Citations for the **Gallantry/Distinguished Services Awards, Compassionate postings, Pre-mature Retirement and Re-employment** of officers posted with the various Cat A Training Establishments of the Army Training Command.

◆ <u>Deputy Director General (Estates)</u>, <u>Chennai Zone (Jun 2019– May 2020)</u>

- Monitored & Directed the recruitment ops of the Indian Army in South India to incl planning & conduct of recruitment rallies, Medicals Tests, Written Exams, Training & Educational progression.
- Effectively organized, planned, coordinated & executed the **Disaster Management Plans with the State Governments** of TN, Karnataka, Telangana & Andhra Pradesh, during 'Op Namaste' Indian Army's Aid to Civil Authorities ops in Southern States during the Covid -19 Pandemic in Yr 2020.

◆ Commander, Independent Infantry Brigade Group , Jammu & Kashmir (Jun 2017 - May 2019)

- As a 'One Star General', responsible for the orchestration of offensive operations into Enemy Territory, along the Northern Front of India.
- Formulated & implemented the HRD Strategy of an Independent Infantry Brigade Group (100 Officers, 350 Junior Commissioned Officer & 8K troops) to incl Work Force Planning & Development, HR Policy, Process & System Design and Systems approach to training (SAT).
- Effectively managed the allocated Central Government Funds upto Rs. 250 Cr (Infrastructure Development & Defence Preparedness) & approx Rs. 50 Cr for procurement of Goods (ACSFP, ACG, Amenity, SAG and Information Technology Funds).
- Planned, organized, directed and controlled the logistics operations for a Brigade Group Sized Force (Approx 7-8K troops) in the difficult and inhospitable terrain of Leh & Ladakh.
- Coordination of own operations with multiple role players to incl civil administration, PMFs (Par Military Forces) and NGOs (Non Government Organizations).

Deputy Brigade Commander, Kasauli (Jun 2016 - May 2017)

- Infrastructure development & maintenance of Kasauli- Jutogh- Dagshai Cantonments, as Smart Military Stations (Townships), leveraging the optimum resource management to include energy conservation, accommodating approx 20-25K personnel.
- Development of cost control techniques, identification of areas with wasteful expenditure or Non-utilization of Resources and exercise post budget vigilance.
- Effectively managed the administration & legal aspect of an Infantry Brigade at Kasauli-Shimla and Dagshai. Responsible for effective management of Veteran Health programs of the GoI (ECHS- Ex Serviceman Contributory Health Scheme) involving multiple Polyclinics in Himachal Pradesh with an Annual Budget of Rs. 8-10 Crs.
- Effectively oversaw the management of **Canteen Stores Depots—Retail Outlets** for serving & retired personnel involving multiple Retail Units & turnover Amounting to Rs. 50 –60 Crs.

◆ <u>Directing Staff, Defence Services Staff College</u>, <u>Wellington</u> (May 2015 - Jun 2016)

• As Directing Staff, responsible for training 100 x Selected Officers of the Indian Army (10 years service bracket), in staff duties to include policy formulation, management of MES & Operational Works, and other miscellaneous duties.

♦ Colonel General Staff, Infantry Division (Jun 2013 - May 2015)

- Formulation of Operational plans, Net assessment and evolution of concepts from future perspective, related to force structure, operational strategies and modernization.
- Render advice & clarification to help compliance of financial policies & CVC Guidelines by the expending authorities to ensure 'Value for Money', 'Economy' & 'Transparency' in procurement of military stores and equipment.

Awards & Accolades

- COAS Commendation Card Awarded for an meticulous planning & conduct of Indo-UK Joint Training Exercise at Salisbury Plains, UK
- VCOAS Commendation Card Awarded for high degree of distinguish service at the Military Operations Directorate, Army Headquarters.
- GOC-in- C Commendation Card Twice awarded, while operating in counter insurgency ops and as a result of direct enemy action during Op Rakshak.
- Force Commanders Commendation Card
 Awarded for contributions towards United Nations peace enforcement operations in MONUC (United nations Mission in Democratic republic of Congo).

Skill & Hobbies

- Quick understanding & appraisal of situations.
- Excellent organizational, interpersonal and articulation skills.
- Proficiency to function in a digitally networked environment.
- Language proficiency fluently in English, Hindi and Punjabi.
- Hobbies Reading & Writing and Sports (Golf, Riding & Polo, Squash and Cricket)

SELF APPRAISAL

- The long military innings has been professionally educative and personally satisfying. The army has equipped me with the capability to:-
 - Comfort unforeseen circumstances and challenges with equanimity and confidence.
 - Operate independently in situations of extreme ambiguity and fluidity.
 - Function effectively under sustained stress and strain for prolonged periods.
 - · Accept adversity as the default operation paradigm.
 - Function as a member of hybrid organizations in a multi-national environment with due regard for diverse work, ethnic, cultural, regional and demographic sensitivities and sensibilities.
 - Steadfastly adhere to the core values of honour, honesty, loyalty, integrity, dedication, commitment and selflessness.
 - Ever ready to undertook any task; 'Har Kam Desh aur Unit (organization) Ke Nam'.
- Deal with superiors, peers, subordinates and stakeholders with dignity and decorum. A keenness to learn, a sunny disposition and a never-say-die attitude have made the journey in the army extremely enjoyable. As I embark on a journey to explore now frontiers of human endeavour, I am confident that I shall be able to take up any challenging assignment in any field and acquit myself honourably.
- ♦ Critical thinker, insatiably Curious & Result Driven.

PERSONAL DETAILS

- DOB 05 October 1969 (52 Years)
- Spouse Ms Gurpreet Kaur, B Ed, MA (English), Punjab University, Chd.
- Address House No-1532, Sector-69, SAS Nagar, Mohali, Punjab—160062.
- Health SHAPE-1
- Affiliations Permanent Member of Wellington Gymkhana Club, Chandigarh Golf Club, Kasauli Club and Defence Services Officers Institute, Chandigarh.

Great leaders are great simplifiers, who offer solutions which everybody understands